<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-03-21T21:25:19+03:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">mralinp</title><subtitle>My awesome blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Khiar ware: sample csgo cheat</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/software/security/game-hacking/2022/03/21/khiar-ware-sample-csgo-cheat.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Khiar ware: sample csgo cheat" /><published>2022-03-21T01:02:05+03:30</published><updated>2022-03-21T01:02:05+03:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/software/security/game-hacking/2022/03/21/khiar-ware-sample-csgo-cheat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/software/security/game-hacking/2022/03/21/khiar-ware-sample-csgo-cheat.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="khiarwarewindows-version">KhiarWare(Windows Version)</h1>
<h2 id="wallhack--triggerbot--radarhack--autobhop">WallHack + TriggerBot + RadarHack + AutoBhop</h2>
<p>This project is an example of game hacking, and it’s created to share the personal experience with other enthusiasts in this branch of software security.<br />
This project is just for educational porpuses and i’m not responsible for any other subversive applications.<br />
As you know game hacking in online games is not allowed owing to annoying some other people. Normal players who just want to have fun with games, don’t want to face a demon hacker in their fun times, so game developers will respond if you do somthing to annoy other players. In other words cheating in online games will cause your account be <strong>banned</strong> (e.g VACation on steam platform).<br /></p>

<p>If you want to run the codes above, compile them with visual studio(i used 2019 edition), and be careful, i don’t guarantee if you are getting banned or not. To be safe while testing and running this code in game, just run the game in <strong>insecure mode</strong>. That turns off the Valve anti-cheat when running the game, but you can’t join any VAC secure servers while launching the game on this mode. To do this just look at <a href="#insecure-mode">Insecure Mode</a>.</p>

<h1 id="how-to-use-this-code">How to use this code</h1>

<p>First of all download the source codes:</p>

<div class="language-console highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gp">foo@bar~:$</span><span class="w"> </span>git clone https://github.com/mralinp/KhiarWare.git  
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Then run <em>updater.py</em>, this will automatically update offset values into <em>Source/Offsets.h</em> file and you have to have <em>requests</em> library installed to run this as well:</p>

<div class="language-console highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gp">foo@bar~:$</span><span class="w"> </span>pip <span class="nb">install </span>requests
<span class="gp">foo@bar~:$</span><span class="w"> </span>python updater.py
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Finally create an empty visual studio project and add all of the source codes into the project (files with .h to Headers and the .cpp files into the Sources). Now you are all set, press run/debug button to execute, enjoy!</p>

<h2 id="insecure-mode">Insecure Mode</h2>
<h3 id="for-those-who-doesnt-want-to-risk-and-its-recommened-by-me">For those who doesn’t want to risk and it’s recommened by me.</h3>
<p>To run this code to see how it’s working without any rish of getting VAC banned, you have to run the game on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">insecure</code> mode.</p>

<p>To do this, open steam, go to library, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">right-click</code> on <strong>CS:GO</strong> icon and choose properties, in  <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">General</code> tab you can see <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Launch options</code> button, click on that and add <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-insecure</code> at the end of the line, done, press <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ok</code> and close the propeties tab.</p>

<p>just remember that for playing normally after testing this code, just remove <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-insecure</code> from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">launch options</code>, this will enables anti-cheat and you are able to play at VAC secure servers.</p>

<p>If you saw that every thing is fine, and it’s working good, you can use this code on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">normal mode</code>, <strong>competetive</strong> or anywhere else, but at you own risk, be careful of being obvious and remember that overwatch is everywhere.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Attention!: Due to CS:GO updates, this source code needs to be updated and adapted with the newest changes, but you can stiil use some parts as a sample of CS:GO cheat.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Ali N. Parizi</name></author><category term="software" /><category term="security" /><category term="game-hacking" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[KhiarWare(Windows Version) WallHack + TriggerBot + RadarHack + AutoBhop This project is an example of game hacking, and it’s created to share the personal experience with other enthusiasts in this branch of software security. This project is just for educational porpuses and i’m not responsible for any other subversive applications. As you know game hacking in online games is not allowed owing to annoying some other people. Normal players who just want to have fun with games, don’t want to face a demon hacker in their fun times, so game developers will respond if you do somthing to annoy other players. In other words cheating in online games will cause your account be banned (e.g VACation on steam platform).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making awesome blog</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/web-development/static-website/jekyll/2022/03/20/making-awesome-blog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making awesome blog" /><published>2022-03-20T20:02:05+03:30</published><updated>2022-03-20T20:02:05+03:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/web-development/static-website/jekyll/2022/03/20/making-awesome-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/web-development/static-website/jekyll/2022/03/20/making-awesome-blog.html"><![CDATA[<p>You’ll find this post in your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_posts</code> directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jekyll serve</code>, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</p>

<p>Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP</code></p>

<p>Where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR</code> is a four-digit number, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MONTH</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">DAY</code> are both two-digit numbers, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MARKUP</code> is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.</p>

<p>Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:</p>

<div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">name</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="n">puts</span> <span class="s">"Hi, #{name}"</span>
<span class="n">end</span>
<span class="n">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'Tom'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="c1">#=&gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.
</span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>Check out the <strong><a href="https://github.com/jekyll/-docs">Jekyll docs</a></strong>  for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at <a href="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll’s GitHub repo</a>. If you have questions, you can ask them on <a href="https://talk.jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll Talk</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ali N. Parizi</name></author><category term="web-development" /><category term="static-website" /><category term="jekyll" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.]]></summary></entry></feed>